Guide to the Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing Records, 1977-1982 UA.10.06.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing records
1977-1982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing
UA.10.06.0002
1.5 Linear Feet
The collection documents the records of the office of the Vice Chancellor for Data Processing for the years 1977 through 1982. The bulk of the materials in the collection pertain to the Administrative System Planning Study, a project that studied the effects an automated computing system would have on the accuracy and efficiency of data processing at Duke. Materials include the final project report as well as drafts tracking the development of the project as well as notes and correspondence from members of the project team. The collection also includes interviews the committee conducted with Duke employees across a wide range of departments and external studies of information management at Duke. The Administrative System Planning Study series contains materials related to the report. They include a copy of the final report and several drafts of the report including notes and revisions. This series also contains two 1982 editions of The Chronicle announcing the institution of a new data processing system on campus. The Project Materials series contains meeting minutes from the Administrative System Planning council, papers as well as correspondence and notes from three members of the committee, Vice-Chancellor Mel Ray, Joe Kuran and Jim Prestwood as they worked to develop the project. These materials also include analyses of the research materials used in the report. The Research Materials series includes information the committee gathered while preparing the report. These materials include 15 interviews with employees from many departments about the current data processing environment at Duke. Interviewees included President Terry Sanford, Chancellor A. Kenneth Pye and Provost F. Cleaveland. Research materials also include the final copies of automation reports completed by IBM Corporation and Hay Associates on the existing systems and the potential effects of automation. Also included is a 1980 issue of IBM Corporation’s magazine, Prospectives in Computing featuring an article about the academic applications of computing at Duke.
Access Restrictions
Records of the University’s Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Provenance
Transfer, 1979-1981
Historical Note
The Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing, Mel Ray, was in charge of managing data and technology at Duke University. In 1977, this department began the Administrative Systems Planning Study. The project was a major effort to establish a system for addressing the near and long-term administrative information needs of the University. Its goals were to study Duke's administrative processes with a view toward identifying how automated information systems might best support administrative operations. The method used was similar to business systems analysis, and involved interviews with key administrators regarding their information needs, and studies of the functioning of existing manual and automated systems.
Collection Overview
The collection documents the records of the office of the Vice Chancellor for Data Processing for the years 1977 through 1982. The bulk of the materials in the collection pertain to the Administrative System Planning Study, a project that studies the effects an automated computing system would have on the accuracy and efficiency of data processing at Duke. Materials related to the Administrative System Planning Study include a copy of the final report, drafts of the report and notes and correspondence between members of the committee.
The collection also contains research materials the committee gathered while preparing the report. These materials include 15 interviews with employees from many departments about the current data processing environment at Duke. Interviewees included President Terry Sanford, Chancellor A. Kenneth Pye and Provost F. Cleaveland. Research materials also include the final copies of automation reports completed by IBM Corporation and Hay Associates on the existing systems and the potential effects of automation. Also included is a 1980 issue of IBM Corporation’s magazine, Prospectives in Computing featuring an article about the academic applications of computing at Duke.
Duke University -- Data processing; Duke University. Office of Information Technology; Duke University Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing; Duke University Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing; Sanford, Terry
- Administrative System Planning Study, 1977-1982; 1
  - Administrative System Planning Study, November 15, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ASP Original, November 15, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ASP Materials, September 13, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative System Planning Project, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Project Materials, 1977-1982; 2
  - Agenda-ASP Council, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Joe Kuran, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jim Prestwood, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mel Ray, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Document Reviews, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Binder Notes, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notes, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ASP-Misc., 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ASP-Interview Analysis (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Research Materials, 1977-1982; 3
  - Interview: Dr. W.G. Anlyan, October 4, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Interview: Delores Burke, October 3, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Interview: Dr. Ewald Busse, September 26, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Interview: Dr. Clark Cahow, October 2, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Interview: Dean Paul Carrington, September 27, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Interview: Provost F. Cleaveland, October 3, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Interview: Mr. Thomas Dixon, September 26, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Interview: Ms. Connie Dunlap, September 29, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Interview: Dr. Jane Elchlepp, September 26, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Interview: Mr. Peyton Fuller, October 2, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Interview: Mr. S.C. Harward, September 28, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Interview: Mr. James Henderson, September 27, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Interview: Mr. Alan Herrick, September 28, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Interview: Mr. Hamilton Hoyer, September 29, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Interview: Mr. Charles B. Huestis, September 27, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Interview: Mr. Richard Jackson, September 26, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Interview: Dean Harold Lewis, October 16, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Interview: Eugene McDonald, October 3, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Interview: Dean John McKinney, September 28, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Interview: Mr. J. Alexander McMahon, September 29, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Interview: Chancellor A. Kenneth Pye, September 27, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Interview: Dr. Roscoe Robinson, October 4, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Interview: Mr. J. Davis Ross, October 3, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Interview: President Terry Sanford, October 2, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Interview: Mr. Robert Winfree, October 2, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - A Study Of the Wage and Salary Administration Function at Duke/Hay Associates, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - A Study in Automation for the Office of the Bursar, July, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - A Study of the Duke University Personnel Management Information System, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Chancellor's Committee on Wage Salary Final Report, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Epoch Campaign: "A Time for Greatness" (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Grads: A Study, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Misc. Source Documents (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Perspectives of Computing IBM. Academic Applications, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Word Processing System Design Study Allen Building. IBM Corp., September 7, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - President's Letter-to Faculty, October 14, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 48)